<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
	-->
<?xml-model href="file:/Users/Benjamin/Desktop/english/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Adventures of Telemachus, the Son of Ulysses</title>
            <author>François Fénelon</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by</resp>
               <name>Benjamin Lowry</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translated into English by</resp>
               <name>Mr. Des Maizeaux, F.R.S.</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>C. Hitch</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>L. Hawes</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>T. Osborne</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>J. Beecroft</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>John Rivington</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>R. Baldwin</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>J. Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>S. Crowder and Co.</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>B. Law</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>T. Longham</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>T. Field</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>T. Caslon</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Printed by</resp>
               <name>C. and R. Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>SMU DeGolyer Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>SMU DeGolyer Library</pubPlace>
            <date>2025-04-10</date>
            <authority>ENGL 3318 student</authority>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>The Adventures of Telemachus, the Son of Ulysses, 1760, SMU DeGolyer Library</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <styleDefDecl scheme="css"
            schemeVersion="2.1" />
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indented" scheme="css">text-indent: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="unindented" scheme="css">text-indent: 0;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="centered" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE</titlePart>
               <titlePart>ADVENTURES</titlePart>
               <titlePart>OF</titlePart>
               <titlePart>TELEMACHUS,</titlePart>
               <titlePart>THE</titlePart>
               <titlePart>SON of ULYSSES.</titlePart>
               <titlePart>BY THE</titlePart>
               <titlePart>ARCHBISHOP of CAMBRAY<note place="foot" n="1">François Fénelon, lived
                  1651-1715, term was 1695-1715</note></titlePart>
               <titlePart>Translated into English by</titlePart>
               <titlePart>Mr. DES MAIZEAUX, F.R.S.</titlePart>
               <!-- TODO: line?-->
               <titlePart>The Third Edition, corrected.</titlePart>
               <!-- TODO: line?-->
               <lb />
               <titlePart rend="small expanded">LONDON:</titlePart>
               <titlePart rend="small">Printed for C. Hitch and L. Hawes, T. Osborne,</titlePart>
               <titlePart rend="small">J. Beecroft, John Rivington, R. Baldwin,</titlePart>
               <titlePart rend="small">J. Ward, S. Crowder and Co. B. Law,</titlePart>
               <titlePart rend="small">T. Longman, T. Field, T. Caslon, and C. and</titlePart>
               <titlePart rend="small">R. Ward.</titlePart>
               <titlePart rend="small">MDCCLX</titlePart>
            </docTitle>

         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb style="hidden" n="i" />
            <head />

            <figure place="top" rend="center" type="printerMark">
               <figDesc>A printer's mark</figDesc>
               <graphic
                  url="https://files.lowryb.sbs/api/public/dl/Bv4JpWw5/Telemachus/539CE0AC-0D69-495D-9FDA-12D51FB6AF89_4_5005_c.jpeg"></graphic>
            </figure>
            <head rend="center">A</head>
            <head rend="center">DISCOURSE<note n="*" place="foot">his discourse has been revised,
               altered and improved in many places, according to corrections communicated by Mr.
               Ramsay<note n="2" place="foot">Potentially Andrew Michael Ramsay, a Scottish writer
               who was close to Fénelon, lived 1686-1743</note>, who is the author of it.</note></head>
            <head rend="center">OF</head>
            <head rend="center">EPIC POETRY,</head>
            <head rend="center">AND OF THE</head>
            <head rend="center">EXCELLENCE</head>
            <head rend="center">Of the POEM of</head>
            <head rend="center">TELEMACHUS</head>

            <p>
               <note type="inset" place="right">The origin and end of poetry.</note>
               <hi rend="large">
               I</hi>F we could relish naked truth, she would not want, to gain our love, the
               ornaments which imagination lends her; but her pure and delicate light does not
               sufficiently sooth the senses of man; she requires an attention which is too
               troublesome to his natural levity. To instruct him, it is necessary to give him not
               only pure ideas which enlighten his mind; but also images which strike his senses,
               and keep his eyes stedfastly fixed on the truth. This is the source of eloquence, of
               poetry, and of all the sciences which belong to the imagination: It is the weakness
               of man which makes these sciences necessary. The plain and unchangeable beauty of
               virtue does not always affect him; it is not sufficient to show him truth; she must
               be painted amiable <note n="(a)" place="foot">Omne tulit punctum qui miscuit utile
               dulci, Lectorem delectando pariterque monendo. Hor. Art. Poet<note n="3" place="foot">"He
               has won every vote who has blended profit and pleasure, at once delighting and
               instructing the reader". Horace, Ars Poetica</note></note>
               <l />
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               We shall examine the poem of Telemachus in these two views, of instructing and
               pleasing; and we shall endeavor to show that the author has instructed more
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="middle">a</fw>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">than</fw>
            <!-- TODO: positioning? -->
            <pb n="ii" rend="align(left)" />
            <p> than the ancients by the sublimity of his moral, and that he has pleased as much as
               they by imitating all their beauties. <l />
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               <note type="inset" place="left">Two forts of heroic poetry.</note>There are two ways
               of instructing men in order to render them good: The first, by showing them the
               deformity of vice, and its fatal consequences, which is the chief design of tragedy:
               The second, by discovering the beauty of virtue and its happy end, which is the
               proper character of the Epopœa or epic poem. The passions which belong to the former,
               are terror and pity; those which agree to the latter, are admiration and love. In
               one, the actors speak; in the other, the poet makes the narration. <l />
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               <note type="inset" place="left">The vision of epic
                  poetry</note> The epic poem may be define, <hi rend="italic">A fable related by a
               poet to raise the
                  admiration, and inspire the love of virtue, by the representation of the action of
               a hero favoured of heaven, who executes a great design by triumphing over all
               obstacles that oppose it. There are therefore three things in the Epopœa, the action,
               the moral, and the poetry.</hi>
               <l />
            </p>
         </div>
         <pb n="1" style="hidden" />
         <div>
            <figure place="top" rend="center" type="printerMark">
               <figDesc>A printer's mark</figDesc>
               <graphic
                  url="https://files.lowryb.sbs/api/public/dl/qaTVeHdE/Telemachus/DD10511B-3610-4D60-98C9-3615CD1B91CF_4_5005_c.jpeg">
               </graphic>
            </figure>
            <head />
            <head rend="center">THE</head>
            <head rend="center">ADVENTURES</head>
            <head rend="center">OF</head>
            <head rend="center">TELEMACHUS,</head>
            <head rend="center">Son of ULYSSES.</head>
            <figure></figure>
            <head rend="center">BOOK the FIRST</head>
            <!-- TODO: line -->
            <p>
               <l rend="center">
                  <hi rend="bold">The <hi rend="expanded">ARGUMENT</hi></hi>
               </l>
               <hi rend="italic">Telemachus guided by Minerva,
                  in the shape of Mentor, gets on shore, after a shipwreck, in the island of the
                  Goddess Calypso, who was still bewailing the departure of Ulysses. The Goddess
                  gives him a kind reception, conceives a passion for him, offers him immortality,
                  and desires of him an account of his adventures. He relates to her his voyage to
                  Pylos and Lacedæmon; his shipwreck on the coast of Sicily; the danger he was in of
                  being sacrificed to the manes of Anchises; the alliance which Mentor and he gave
                  Aceltes in an incursion of Barbarians, and the care which this King took to
                  requite their service, by giving them a Tyrian ship to return to their own
                  country.</hi>
               <lb />
               <lb />
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="large">C</hi>ALYPSO could not be comforted for the departure of Ulysses: in
               her grief she found herself unhappy by being immortal. Her grotto no longer echoed
               with the sweet music of her voice: the nymphs who attended her dared not speak to
               her. She often walked alone on the flowery turf, with which an eternal spring
               surrounded her island: but these beautiful scenes, far from alleviating her sorrow,
               did but recall to her the sad remembrance of Ulysses, whom she there had seen so many
               times with her. She often stood motion- </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="middle">b 3</fw>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">less</fw>

            <pb n="2" rend="left" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="left">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               less on the sea shore, which she watered with her tears, and was continually turned
               towards the part where the ship of Ulysses, ploughing the waves, had disappeared from
               her eyes. On a sudden she perceived the fragments of a vessel that had just been
               wrecked, rowers benches broken in pieces, oars scattered here and there on the sand,
               a rudder, a mast and cordage floating on the shore. Then she descried two men at a
               distance; one of them seemed in years, the other, though young, resembled Ulysses. He
               had his sweet and noble aspect, with his stature and majestic port. The Goddess knew
               him to be Telemachus, the son of that hero: but though the Gods far surpass all men
               in knowledge, she could not discover who the venerable person was by whom Telemachus
               was attended; because the superior Gods conceal from the inferior whatever they
               please; and Minerva, who accompanied Telemachus in the shape of Mentor, would not be
               known by Calypso. Mean time Calypso rejoiced at a wreck which brought the son of
               Ulysses, so like his father, into her island. She advances towards him, and without
               seeming to know who he is, What inspires you, says she to him, with the presumption
               to land in my island? Know young stranger, that none enters my empire unpunished. She
               endeavored to hide under these threatening words the joy of her heart, which in spite
               of her appeared in her face.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Telemachus answered, O! whoever you are, whether a mortal or a
               Goddess (though none can see and not take you for a deity) can you be insensible to
               the misfortunes of a son, who, seeking his father through perils of winds and waves,
               has seen his vessel split against your rocks? Who then is the father you are in quest
               of, replied the Goddess? He is called Ulysses, said Telemachus; he is one of the
               kings, who have, after a ten years siege, subverted the famous Troy. His name was
               renowned through all Greece and Asia for his valour in combat, and yet more for his
               wisdom in council. Now wandering o'er the whole extent of seas, he runs through all
               the most terrible dangers. His country seems to fly before him. Penelope his wife,
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">and</fw>

            <pb n="3" rend="right" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="right">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               and I his son, have lost all hopes of ever seeing him again, I am running the same
               hazards as he, to learn where he is. But, what do I say! perhaps he is now buried in
               the profound abysses of the sea. Pity our woes; and, O Goddess! if you know what the
               destinies have done either to save or destroy Ulysses, deign to inform his son
               Telemachus of it.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Calypso, surprized and moved at finding so much wisdom and
               eloquence in such blooming youth, could not satisfy her eyes with looking upon him,
               and remained silent. At length she said to him, We will inform you, Telemachus, what
               has befallen your father; but the history of it is long, and it is time for you to
               refresh yourself after your toils. Come into the place of my abode, where I will
               receive you as my son: come, you shall be my comfort in this solitude; and I will
               procure you happiness, if you know how to enjoy it.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Telemachus followed the goddess, incircled by a crowd of young
               nymphs, above whom she raised her whole head, as a large oak in a forest rases its
               thick branches above all the surrounding trees. He admired the lustre of her beauty,
               the rich purple of her long flowing robe, her hair tied with graceful negligence
               behind the fire which flashed from her eyes, and the mildness which tempered its
               vivacity. Mentor, with downcast eyes and a modest silence, followed Telemachus.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               They came to the entrance of Calypso's grotto, where
               Telemachus was surprized to see, with an appearance of rural simplicity, all that can
               charm the eye. There was seen indeed neither gold, not silver, nor marble, nor
               columns, not pictures, not statues; the grotto was hewn out of the rock, in arches
               lined with shells and pebbles; its tapestry was a young vine which extended its
               pliant branches equally on all sides. Gentle Zephirs here maintained, in spite of the
               beams of the Sun, a delightful coolness. fountains sweetly purling thro' meadows sown
               with amaranths and violets, formed, in various places, baths as pure and clear as
               chrystal. A thousand springing flowers enamelled the verdant car-
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="middle">b 4</fw>
            <fw type="footer" place="left">pets</fw>

            <pb n="4" rend="left" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="right">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               pets which surrounded the grotto. There was found a whole wood of those tufted trees
               which beat apples of gold, and whose blossoms, which are renewed in all seasons, shed
               the sweetest of all perfumes. This wood seemed to crown those beautiful meads, and
               formed a shade which the rays of the Sun could not penetrate. Here nothing was ever
               heard but the warbling of birds, or the murmurs of a brook, which, rushing from the
               top of a rock, fell in large and frothy streams, and fled across the meadow.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented"> The Goddess's grotto was on the declivity of a hill, from
               whence one beheld the sea, sometimes clear and smooth as glass, sometimes idly
               irritated against the rocks on which it broke bellowing, and swelling its waves like
               mountains. From another side was seen a river, in which were islands bordered with
               blooming limes, and lofty poplars, which raised their haughty heads even to the
               clouds. The several channels, which formed those islands, seemed sporting in the
               plain. Some rolled their limpid waters with rapidity; some had a peaceful and sleepy
               stream; others by long windings ran back again, to re-ascend as it were to their
               source, and seemed not to have power to leave these enchanting borders. At a distance
               were seen hills and mountains, which lost themselves in the clouds, and formed, by
               their fantastic figures, as delightful an horizon as the eye could wish to behold.
               The neighbouring mountains, where covered with verdant vine branches, hanging in
               festoons<note place="foot" n="4">a chain or garland of flowers, leaves, or
                  ribbons, hung in a curve as a
                  decoration.</note>; the grapes, brighter than purple, could not conceal themselves
               under the leaves, and the vine was over-loaded with its fruit. The fig, the olive,
               the pomgranate, and all other trees, over-spread the plain, and made it a large
               garden. </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Calypso, having shown Telemachus, all these natural beauties,
               said to him, Repose yourself, your garments are wet, it is time for you to change
               them; afterwards I will see you again, and relate things with which your heart will
               be touched. The Goddess then caused him and Mentor to enter into the most secret and
               retired part of a grotto next to that in which she herself resided.
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">In</fw>

            <pb n="5" rend="right" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="left">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               In this apartment the nymphs had taken care to light a great fire of cedar-wood,
               whose fragrant odour diffused itself on all sides, and had left vestments in it for
               their new guests. Telemachus, seeing they had alloted him a tunic of fine wool, whose
               whiteness eclipsed that of snow, and a purple robe embroidered with gold, took the
               pleasure which is natural to youth, in viewing their magnificence.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Mentor said to him in a grave tone, Are these, Telemachus, the
               thoughts which ought to possess the heart of the son of Ulysses? Think rather of
               supporting your father's reputation and of conquering the fortune which persecutes
               you. A young man who loves to deck himself vainly like a woman, is unworthy of wisdom
               and glory: glory is due only to a soul which knows to bear pain, and trample
               pleasures under foot.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Telemachus answered sighing, May the Gods destroy me rather than suffer luxury and
               voluptuousness to take possession of my heart: no, no, the son of Ulysses shall never
               be vanquished by the charms of a soft and an effiminate life. But how gracious is
               heaven in directing us, after our shipwreck, to this Goddess, or this mortal, who
               loads us with benefits!
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Fear, replied Mentor, lest she load you with evils: fear her sweet, deceitful words
               more than the rocks which dashed your vessel in pieces. Shipwreck and death are less
               fatal than pleasures which attack virtue. Take heed not to credit what she will
               relate to you. Youth is presumptuous; it hopes every thing from itself; though frail,
               it thinks itself all-sufficient, and that it has never any thing to fear; it is
               credulous and unwary. Be sure not to regard Calypso's sweet and flattering words,
               which will insinuate themselves like a serpent under flowers. Suspect their hidden
               poison, mistrust yourself, and always wait for my advice.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               After this, they returned to Calypso, who was waiting for them. The nymphs with
               braided hair and white vestments immediately served up a plain repast, but exquisite
               with regard to its taste and elegance. There was no flesh but that of birds which
               they had
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="middle">b 5</fw>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">taken</fw>

            <pb n="6" rend="left" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="right">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               taken in their nets, or of beasts which they had killed with their arrows in the
               chace. Wine, more delicious than nectar, flowed from large silver vases into golden
               cups crowned with flowers. There were brought in baskets all the fruits which the
               spring promises, and autumn lavishes on the earth. At the same time four young nymphs
               began to sing. They first sung the war of the Gods against the giants; then the loves
               of Jupiter and Semele; the birth of Bacchus, and his education under old Silenus; the
               race of Atalanta and Hippomenes, who was conqueror by means of the golden apples
               gathered in the gardens of Hesperides: at last the Trojan war was likewise sung, and
               the combats and wisdom of Ulysses extolled to the skies. The chief of the nymphs,
               whose name was Leucothoë, joined the harmony of her lyre to the sweet voices of all
               the others. When Telemachus heard the name of his father, the tears which ran down
               his cheeks gave a new lustre to his beauty. But as Calypso perceived that he could
               not eat, and that he was seized with grief, she made a sign to the nymphs; upon which
               they sung the battle of the Centaurs with the Lapithæ, and the descent of Orpheus to
               hell to fetch his dear Eurydice from thence.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               When the repast was ended, the Goddess took Telemachus aside, and bespoke him thus:
               You see, son of the great Ulysses, with what favour I receive you; I am immortal; no
               man can enter this island without being punished for his temerity; and even you
               shipwreck would not save you from my indignation, if I did not moreover love you.
               Your father had the same good fortune as you; but alas! he was not wise enough to
               turn it to his advantage. I detained him a long while in this island; he might here
               have lived with me in a state of immortality; but the blind passion of returning to
               his wretched country, made him reject all these advantages. You see all he has lost
               for Ithaca, which he will never see again. He was resolved to leave me; he departed,
               and I was revenged by the tempest: his vessel, having long been the sport of the
               winds, was buried in the waves. Make a right use of so sad an ex-
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">ample.</fw>

            <pb n="7" rend="right" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="left">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               ample. After his shipwreck you can have no hopes of either seeing him again, or of
               ever reigning in the island of Ithaca after him; be not afflicted at his loss, since
               you find a Goddess ready to make you happy, and a kingdom which she offers you. To
               these words Calypso added a long discourse, to show how happy, Ulysses had been with
               her. She recited his adventures in the cave of Polyphemus the Cyclop, and in the
               country of Antiphates king of the Lestrigons. She forgot not what happened to him in
               the island of Circe the daughter of the Sun, and the dangers he was in between Scylla
               and Charybdis. She described the last storm which Neptune had raised against him when
               he departed from her; and designing to make Telemachus think that he perished in this
               tempest, she suppressed his arrival in the island of the Phæcians.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Telemachus, who had at first too hastily abandoned himself to
               joy at being so well treated by Calypso, at length perceived her artifice, and the
               wisdom of the counsels which Mentor had just given him. He replied in a few words, O
               Goddess, excuse my sorrow. I may be more able to relish the happiness you offer me.
               Permit me now to weep for my father. You know better than I how much he deserves to
               be lamented.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Calypso, not daring to urge him further at first, pretended even to sympathize with
               him in his grief, and to pity Ulysses. But the better to know the means of winning
               the heart of the youth, she asked him how he was wrecked, and by what accidents he
               was on her coasts. The relation of my misfortunes, said he, would be too tedious. No,
               no, replied she, I long to know them; make haste to relate them to me. She pressed
               him a long while: at length, not being able to deny her, he began thus:
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               I left Ithaca in order to go and inquire of the other kings returned from the siege
               of Troy news of my father. My mother Penelope's suitors were surprised at my
               departure; for knowing their treachery, I had taken care to conceal it from them.
               Nestor, whom I saw at Pylos, nor Menelaus, who received me in a
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">friendly</fw>

            <pb n="8" rend="left" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="right">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               friendly manner at Lacedæmon, could inform me whether my father was still alive.
               Weary of living continually in suspence and incertainty, I resolved to go into
               Sicily, where I had heard that my father had been driven by the winds. But the sage
               Mentor, whom you see here present, opposed this rash design; representing to me the
               Cyclops, monstrous giants, who devour men, on the one side; on the other, the fleet
               of Æneas and the Trojans, said he, are exasperated against all the Greeks, and would
               take a singular pleasure in shedding the blood of the son of Ulysses. Return,
               continued he, to Ithaca; perhaps your father, beloved of the Gods, will be there as
               soon as you; but if the Gods have decreed his destruction, if he must never see his
               country again, you should at least go to revenge him, to set your mother at liberty,
               to manifest your wisdom to the world, and to let all Greece see in you a king as
               worthy of reigning as ever Ulysses himself was. These were salutary words; but I was
               not wise enough to listen to them; I listened only to my passions. The sage Mentor
               loved me so well as to attend me in this rash voyage, which I undertook contrary to
               his counsel; and the Gods permitted me to commit a fault, which was to cure me of my
               presumption.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Whilst Telemachus was speaking, Calypso gazed at Mentor. She was astonished; and
               fancied she perceived in him something divine; but she could not clear up the
               confusion of her thoughts. She remained therefore full of fear and suspicion at the
               sight of this stranger. And being apprehensive that she should discover her disorder,
               Go on, said she to Telemachus, and satisfy my curiosity. Telemachus thus resumed his
               story:
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               We had for a long time a favourable wind for sailing to Sicily; but at last a black
               tempest ravished the heavens from our eyes, and we were involved in a profound night.
               By the flashes of lightning we discovered other ships exposed to the same danger, and
               presently knew that they were Æneas's fleet; no less formidable to us than the rocks
               themselves. Then I perceived, but too
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">late,</fw>

            <pb n="9" rend="right" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="left">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               late, what the heat of my imprudent youth had hindered me from considering with
               attention. Mentor appeared in this danger not only firm and intrepid, but more gay
               than usual. it was he who encouraged me, and I was sensible that he inspired me with
               an invincible fortitude. He gave out all orders with tranquility, while the pilot was
               at a loss what to do. Dear Mentor, said I, why did I refuse to yield to your
               counsels? How wretched I am in following my own, at an age when one has no foresight
               of the future, no experience of the past, nor wisdom to govern the present? O! should
               we ever escape this tempest, I will mistrust myself as my most dangerous enemy; you,
               Mentor, shall always rule me.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Mentor replied with a smile, I am far from reproaching you with the fault you have
               committed; it suffices that you are sensible of it, and that it will teach you
               another time to curb your desires. But when the danger is over, your presumption
               perhaps will return. We must however at present support ourselves by out courage.
               Before we run into danger, we should foresee and apprehend it; but when one is in it,
               we have nothing to do but despise it. Be therefore the worthy son of Ulysses, and
               manifest a courage superior to all the dangers which threaten you.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               The good-nature and courage of Mentor charmed me; but I was still much more
               surprised, when I saw with what dexterity he delivered us from the Trojans. The
               moment the heavens began to clear up, and the Trojans seeing us near could not but
               have known us, he observed one of their ships, which nearly resembled ours, and had
               been separated by the storm, whose stern was crowned with certain flowers. He
               immediately placed garlands of the like flowers upon our stern; he tied them himself
               with ribbands of the same colour as those of the Trojans, and ordered all our rowers
               to stoop as close as possible to their benches, that they might not be known by the
               enemy. In this condition we passed through the midst of their fleet, while they
               shouted for joy at seeing us, as though they had seen their companions whom they
               thought they had lost: nay, we were constrained, by the violence of the sea, to sail
               a
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">good</fw>

            <pb n="10" rend="left" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="right">Book I.</fw>
            <p> good while along with them. At last we staid a little behind; and whilst the
               impetous winds drove them towards Africa, we made our utmost efforts to land by dint<note
                  place="foot" n="5">A
                  blow or stroke</note> of rowing on the neighbouring coasts of Sicily. </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               We indeed arrived there, but what we fought was no less fatal than the fleet which
               occasioned our flight. We had found on this coast of Sicily other Trojans, and
               consequently enemies of the Greeks. Here reigned old Acestes, who sprung from Troy.
               We had hardly reached the shore, but the inhabitants, supporting us either other
               people of the island who had taken arms to surprise them, or foreigners who came to
               seize their lands, burn our vessel in the first transport of their rage, and
               murdered all our companions; reserving only Mentor and myself to present us to
               Acestes, that he might learn from us what were our designs, and from whence we came.
               We entered the city with our hands tied behind our backs, and our death was deferred
               only that we might serve for a sight to a cruel people, when they should know that we
               were Greeks.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               We were immediately presented to Acestes, who holding his golden scepter in his hand,
               was administering justice among the people, and preparing for a grand sacrifice. He
               asked us, in a stern voice, Of what country we were, and the occasion of our voyage?
               Mentor immediately replied, and said to him, We come from the coast of Great
               Hesperia, and our country is not far from thence. Thus he avoided saying that we were
               Greeks. But Acestes, without hearing any thing more, and taking us for foreigners who
               concealed our design, ordered us to be sent into a neighbouring forest, to serve as
               slaves under those who attended his flocks. This condition appearing to me more
               intolerable than death, O king, cried I, put us to death rather than treat us thus
               unworthily. Know that I am Telemachus, the son of the sage Ulysses, king of the
               Ithacans; I am seeking my father in every sea; if I can neither find him, nor return
               to my native country, nor avoid slavery, take from me a life which I cannot support.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               I had hardly uttered these words, when all the enraged people cried out, That they
               ought to put to death
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">the</fw>

            <pb n="11" rend="right" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="left">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               the son of the cruel Ulysses, whose artifices had overthrown the city of Troy. O son
               of Ulysses, said Acestes to me, I cannot refuse your blood to the manes of the many
               Trojans, whom your father has sent to the banks of the black Cocytus; you, and he
               who conducts you, shall die. At the same time and old man of the company advised the
               king to sacrifice us on the tomb of Anchises. Their blood, said he, will be grateful
               to the shade of that hero; Æneas himself, when he shall hear of such a sacrifice,
               will rejoice to see how much you love what of all things in the world was the dearest
               to him. All the people applauded this proposition, and thought of nothing but of
               sacrificing us. They were already leading us to the tomb of Anchises; they had there
               erected two altars, on which the holy fire was kindled; the knife which was to slay
               us was before our eyes; we were crowned with flowers; no pity could save our lives;
               our fate was determined; when Mentor, calmly desiring leave to speak to the king,
               said to him:
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               O Acestes, if the misfortunes of the youthful Telemachus, who never bore arms against
               the Trojans, cannot move you; at least let your own interest move you. The knowledge
               I have obtained of presages and the will of the Gods, informs me, that before three
               days are elapsed, you will be attacked by barbarous nations, which are coming like a
               torrent from the tops of the mountains to overflow your city, and to ravage all your
               country. Make haste to prevent them; put your subjects under arms, and delay not a
               moment to drive within your walls the rich flocks and herds which you have in the
               fields. If my prediction is false, you will be at liberty to sacrifice us in three
               days; if, on the contrary, it is true, you will remember that you ought not to take
               away the life of those to whom you owe your own.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Acestes was astonished at these words, which Mentor pronounced with a confidence
               which he had never found in any man. I plainly perceive, O stranger, replied he, that
               the Gods, who have allotted you so small a portion of the gifts of fortune, have
               given you a wisdom which is more valuable than the greatest prosperity. At the same
               time he put off the sacrifice, and immediately gave
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">the</fw>

            <pb n="12" rend="left" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="right">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               the orders which were necessary to prevent the attack, with which Mentor had
               threatened him. Nothing was seen on every side but trembling women, men bowed down
               with age, and little children with tears in their eyes, retiring into the city. Herds
               of lowing oxen and flocks of bleating sheep came in crowds, quitting their fat
               pastures, and unable to find stabling enough to receive them. There was in all parts
               a confused noise of men, who pressed upon and could not understand each other, who
               took in this confusion a stranger for their friend, and who run without knowing
               whither they were going. But the chiefs of the city, conceiting themselves wiser than
               the rest, imagined that Mentor was an impostor, who had made a false prediction to
               save his life.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Before the end of the third day, whilst they were full of these thoughts, there were
               seen, on the descent of the neighbouring mountains, a curling cloud of dust; then
               they perceived an innumerable host of armed barbarians. They were the Hymerians, a
               savage people, with the nations which inhabit the Nebrodian mountains, and the top of
               Agragas, where a winter reigns which was never softened by the Zephirs. They who had
               despised Mentor's prediction, lost their slaves and their flocks. The king said to
               Mentor, I forget that you are Greeks; our enemies are become our faithful friends;
               the Gods have sent you to save us; I do not expect less from you valour than from the
               wisdom of your counsels; make haste to succour us.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               Mentor discovers in his eyes an intrepidity which astonishes the fiercest warriors.
               He takes a buckler, a helmet, a sword and lance; he marshals the soldiers of Acestes;
               he marches at their head, and advances in good order towards the enemy. Acestes,
               though full of courage, can by reason of his age only follow him at a distance. I
               follow him closer, but cannot equal his valour. In the battle his cuirass resembled
               the immortal Ægis. Death ran from rank to rank wherever his blows descended: so a
               Numidian lion, stung with hunger, falls on a flock of feeble sheep, he rends, he
               slays, he swims in blood, and the sheperds, in-
            </p>
            <fw type="footer" place="right">stead</fw>

            <pb n="13" rend="right" />
            <fw type="header" rend="bold" place="center">TELEMACHUS</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="left">Book I.</fw>
            <p>
               stead of succouring the flock, fly trembling to escape his fury.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               The Barbarians, who hoped to surprise the city, were themselves surprised and thrown
               into disorder. The subjects of Acestes, animated by Mentor's words and valour, felt a
               vigour of which they thought themselves incapable. With my lance I killed the son of
               the enemy's king; he was of my age, but he was taller than I; for these people are
               descended from a race of giants of the same origin as the Cyclops. He despised so
               weak an adversary as me. But without being alarmed at his prodigious strength or
               savage brutal air, I thrust my lance against his breast, and made him as he expired
               vomit forth torrents of black blood. He had like to have crushed me in his fall. The
               clattering of his arms resounded in the mountains. I took the spoils, and returned to
               find Acestes. Mentor, having intirely routed the enemy, cut them in pieces, and
               pursued the fugitives even into the woods.
            </p>
            <p rendition="#indented">
               This so unexpected success made Mentor looked upon as a man beloved and inspired by
               the Gods. Acestes, touched with gratitude, told us, that he should be in the greatest
               fear for us, if Æneas's fleet should return to Sicily. He gave us a ship to return
               without delay to our own country, loaded us with presents, and pressed us to depart,
               in order to prevent the evils he foresaw. But not caring to give us either a pilot or
               rowers of his own nation, for fear they should be too much exposed upon the coast of
               Greece, he provided for us some Phœnician merchants, who, trading with all the
               nations of the world, had nothing to fear, and were to bring back the vessel to
               Acestes, when the had left us in Ithaca: But the Gods, who sport with the designs of
               men, reserved us for other misfortunes.
            </p>
            <l rend="bold italic large center">End of the First Book</l>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
